[
    {
        "question": "In India ............... laid the foundation of film making in 1913.",
        "options": [
            "Gopal Hari Deshmukh",
            "Aga Khan",
            "Dada Saheb Phalke",
            "Rabindranath Tagore"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": " ............... sung by Rabindranath Tagore is used as audio source of history.",
        "options": [
            "Jhanda Uncha rahe hamara",
            "Vande Mataram",
            "Sare Jahan se accha",
            "Jana Gana Mana"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "During the British period newspapers were not only the source of ............... events but also acted as a source of social reformation.",
        "options": [
            "Religious",
            "Political",
            "Cultural",
            "Economic"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Shatapatre by Lokahitawadi were published in the weekly ..............",
        "options": [
            "Dnyanoday",
            "Dnyanprakash",
            "Prabhakar",
            "Deenbandhu"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "Visiting Manibhavan in Mumbai we get information about the history of ............... era.",
        "options": [
            "Panditji",
            "Medieval",
            "Modern",
            "Gandhian"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": " ............... is also regarded as an important source of history.",
        "options": [
            "Drawings",
            "Map",
            "Survey",
            "Janata"
        ],
        "answer": 2 
    },
    {
        "question": "We find comments on various social and cultural issues in ‘Nibandhmala’ by ...............",
        "options": [
            "Krishnashashtri Chiplunkar",
            "Vishnushastri Chiplunkar",
            "Lokmanya Tilak",
            "Gopal Hari Deshmukh"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "............... was composed on freedom struggle of 1857.",
        "options": [
            "Music",
            "Songs",
            "Powadas",
            "Bhajans"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The survey of India was an independent department established during the ............... period.",
        "options": [
            "Indian",
            "British",
            "Modern",
            "Ancient"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "............... provide us information about the contemporary events.",
        "options": [
            "Audio",
            "Video",
            "Newspapers",
            "Social"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "In the pre-independence period newspapers like .............. acted as important source of awakening the minds of the people.",
        "options": [
            "Kesari",
            "Hindu",
            "Darpan",
            "Hindustan"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": ".............. sources include material, written and oral sources.",
        "options": [
            "Geographical",
            "Historical",
            "Audio",
            "Modern"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Some are declared as national monument, where as some are converted into ...............",
        "options": [
            "Government",
            "Office",
            "Museum",
            "Residence"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The period of ............... Indian History is believed as period of European especially the British rulers and governance of princely states.",
        "options": [
            "Ancient",
            "Modern",
            "Medieval"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "The ............... of technique of recording was also as important as photography.",
        "options": [
            "Invention",
            "Explore",
            "Discovery",
            "Speeches"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "There ............... are also important for the study of modern Indian history.",
        "options": [
            "Museum",
            "Painting",
            "Statues",
            "Plaque"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "In April 1927, Dr. Ambedkar started the newspaper ...............",
        "options": [
            "Kesari",
            "Mahratta",
            "Mooknayak",
            "Bahishkrut Bharat"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "The plans designed by the ............... prove important from the view of study of architecture of a building",
        "options": [
            "Engineer",
            "Architects"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "The Powadas were used to create .............. and spirit among the people.",
        "options": [
            "Motivation",
            "Inspiration",
            "Event",
            "Features"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "During the visit of ............... jail in Andaman we get information about the revolutionary work of V.D. Savarkar",
        "options": [
            "Cellular",
            "Sevagram",
            "Criminal",
            "Civil"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": " At the ............... in Pune, we can see different objects, documents giving information about the life of Mahatma Gandhi",
        "options": [
            "Sevagram Ashram",
            "Manibhavan",
            "Aga Khan Palace"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "Photographs are ............... sources of Modern India History.",
        "options": [
            "Video",
            "Audio",
            "Visual",
            "Audio Visual"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The display ................ on the statues gives us information about the full name of the concerned person.",
        "options": [
            "Museum",
            "Plaque",
            "Painting",
            "Cell"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": " ............... is a source for getting information about a historical event or the work of a person.",
        "options": [
            "Architects",
            "Engineers",
            "Powada",
            "Folk Songs"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "Recording is a form of ............... source of history.",
        "options": [
            "Audio",
            "Video",
            "Visual",
            "Audio Visual"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    }
]